It's amazing, when you meet a head of state and you say,
إنه لأمر مدهش ، عندما تلتقي رئيس دولة و تقول
"What is your most precious natural resource?" --
: "ما هو أثمن مورد طبيعي بالنسبة لك؟" --
they will not say children at first.
لن يقول الأطفال في البداية.
And then when you say children,
ثم عندما تقول له الأطفال ،
they will pretty quickly agree with you.
، فإنه سرعان ما يتفق معك.
(Video): We're traveling today with
(فيديو): نحن نسافر اليوم مع
the Minister of Defense of Colombia,
وزير الدفاع الكولمبي،
head of the army and the head of the police,
قائد الجيش وقائد الشرطة،
and we're dropping off 650 laptops
وسنقوم بنقل 650 كمبيوتر محمول
today to children
اليوم الى الإطفال
who have no television, no telephone
الذين ليس لديهم تلفاز أو هاتف
and have been in a community
وكانوا في مجتمع
cut off from the rest of the world
معزول عن بقية العالم
for the past 40 years.
للأربعين سنة الماضية.
The importance of delivering laptops to this region
أهمية إرسال الكمبيوترات الى هذه المنطقة
is connecting kids who have otherwise been unconnected
هي ربط الأطفال الذين بخلاف ذلك سيكونوا معزولين
because of the FARC,
بسبب العصابات الثورية،
the guerrillas that started off 40 years ago
المليشيات التي أنطلقت قبل 40 عاماً مضت
as a political movement and then became a drug movement.
كحركة سياسية وتحولت الى حركة مخدرات.
There are one billion children in the world,
هناك مليار طفل في العالم،
and 50 percent of them don't have electricity
وخمسون في المائة منهم ليس لديه كهرباء
at home or at school.
في المنزل أو المدرسة.
And in some countries -- let me pick Afghanistan --
وفي بعض البلدان -- أسمحوا لي بإختيار أفغانستان --
75 percent of the little girls don't go to school.
75 في المائة من الفتيات الصغيرات لا يذهبن الى المدرسة.
And I don't mean that they drop out of school
ولا أعني أنهن يتركن المدرسة
in the third or fourth grade -- they don't go.
في الصف الثالث أو الرابع -- لا يدخلن أساساً.
So in the three years
إذاً قبل ثلاث سنوات
since I talked at TED and showed a prototype,
منذ أن تحدثت في تيد وعرضت النموذج،
it's gone from an idea
تحول الأمر من فكرة
to a real laptop.
الى كمبيوتر محمول حقيقي.
We have half a million laptops today
لدينا نصف مليون كمبيوتر محمول اليوم
in the hands of children.
في أيدي الأطفال.
We have about a quarter of a million in transit
لدينا حوالي ربع مليون في الطريق
to those and other children,
الى هؤلاء وأطفال آخرين،
and then there are another quarter of a million more
وبعد ذلك هناك ربع مليون أخرى
that are being ordered at this moment.
تم طلبها في هذه اللحظة.
So, in rough numbers, there are a million laptops.
إذاً، بارقام تقريبية، هناك مليون كمبيوتر محمول.
That's smaller than I predicted --
ذلك أقل مما توقعت --
I predicted three to 10 million --
توقعت ثلاثة الى 10 ملايين --
but is still a very large number.
لكنه يظل عدداً ضخماً.
In Colombia, we have about 3,000 laptops.
في كولمبيا، لدينا حوالي 3 آلالاف كمبيوتر محمول.
It's the Minister of Defense with whom we're working,
أنه وزير الدفاع الشخص الذي نعمل معه،
not the Minister of Education, because it is seen as
ليس وزير التعليم، لأنه يعتبر
a strategic defense issue
كقضية دفاع إستراتيجي
in the sense of liberating these zones
بمعنى تحرير هذه المناطق
that had been completely closed off,
التي كانت معزولة تماماً،
in which the people who had been causing, if you will,
التي عاش فيها الناس، اذا صح التعبير،
40 years' worth of bombings and kidnappings
لمدة أربعين عاماً من التفجيرات والخطف
and assassinations lived.
والإغتيالات، كما هو.
And suddenly,
وفجأة،
the kids have connected laptops.
تم ربط الأطفال بكمبيوترات محمولة.
They've leapfrogged.
لقد تفوقوا.
The change is absolutely monumental,
التغيير بالطبع هائل،
because it's not just opening it up,
لأنه ليس مجرد فتح الباب،
but it's opening it up to the rest of the world.
لكنه فتح الباب أمام بقية العالم.
So yes, they're building roads, yes, they're putting in telephone,
إذاً نعم، أنهم يشيدون الطرق، نعم، أنهم ينشئون الهواتف،
yes, there will be television.
نعم، سيكون هناك تلفاز.
But the kids six to 12 years old
لكن الأطفال من عمر 6 الى 12
are surfing the Internet in Spanish and in local languages,
يستكشفون الإنترنت باللغة الأسبانية واللغات المحلية،
so the children grow up
إذا ينشأ الأطفال
with access to information,
مع إمكانية الوصول إلى المعلومات.
with a window into the rest of the world.
مع نافذة الى بقية العالم.
Before, they were closed off.
في السابق، كانوا معزولين.
Interestingly enough, in other countries,
والمثير للإهتمام، في بقية البلدان،
it will be the Minister of Finance who sees it
سيكون وزير المالية هو الذي يرى الأمر
as an engine of economic growth.
كمحرك للنمو الإقتصادي.
And that engine is going to see the results in 20 years.
وذلك المحرك سيشهد النتائج خلال 20 عاماً.
It's not going to happen, you know, in one year,
ذلك لن يحصل، تعرفون، في سنة،
but it's an important, deeply economic
لكنه تغيير مهم، إقتصادي
and cultural change
وتغيير ثقافي
that happens through children.
يحدث عبر الأطفال.
Thirty-one countries in total are involved,
31 دولة في المجمل ضالعة
and in the case of Uruguay,
وفي حالة الأرغواي،
half the children already have them,
حصل نصف الأطفال بالفعل عليها،
and by the middle of 2009,
وبحلول منتصف عام 2009،
every single child in Uruguay will have a laptop --
سيحصل كل طفل في الأرغواي على كمبيوتر محمول --
a little green laptop.
كمبيوتر محمول أخضر صغير.
Now what are some of the results?
الآن ما هي النتائج؟
Some of the results
بعض النتائج
that go across every single country
التي تحدث في كل دولة
include teachers saying
تتضمن مقولة المعلمين
they have never loved teaching so much,
أنهم لم يحبوا التدريس كثيراً،
and reading comprehension
وقراءة الإنشاء
measured by third parties -- not by us -- skyrockets.
بتقييم أناس آخرين -- ليس نحن -- مضيئة.
Probably the most important thing we see
محتمل أن أهم شئ نراه
is children teaching parents.
هو تعليم الأطفال لآبائهم.
They own the laptops. They take them home.
أنهم يملكون كمبيوترات محمولة. يأخذونها الى البيت.
And so when I met with three children from the schools,
وعليه إلتقيت مع ثلاثة أطفال من المدارس،
who had traveled all day to come to Bogota,
الذين ينتقلوا طوال اليوم ليصلوا الى بوجوتا،
one of the three children brought her mother.
أحدى الاطفال الثلاث جلبت والدتها.
And the reason she brought her mother
وسبب جلبها لأمها
is that this six-year-old child
أن هذه الطفلة ذات الست سنوات
had been teaching her mother
كانت تعلّم والدتها
how to read and write.
كيف تقرأ وتكتب.
Her mother had not gone to primary school.
لم تذهب والدتها الى المدرسة الإبتدائية.
And this is such an inversion,
وهذا مثل التحوّل،
and such a wonderful example
وهذا المثال الرائع
of children being the agents of change.
للأطفال يصبحون عوامل التغيير.
So now, in closing, people say,
إذاً الآن، في الختام، يقول الناس،
now why laptops?
الآن لماذا كمبيوترات محمولة؟
Laptops are a luxury; it's like giving them iPods. No.
أنها ترف. أنها مثل منحهم جهاز آي بود. لا.
The reason you want laptops
سبب الحوجة للكمبيوترات المحمولة
is that the word is education, not laptop.
أن الهدف هو التعليم، ليس كمبيوتر محمول.
This is an education project, not a laptop project.
هذا مشروع تعليمي، ليس مشروع كمبيوتر محمول.
They need to learn learning. And then, just think --
يحتاجون لدراسة التعلم. وثم، فقط فكّر --
they can have, let's say, 100 books.
يمكنهم الحصول، لنقول، مائة كتاب.
In a village, you have 100 laptops,
في القرية، لديكم مائة كمبيوتر محمول،
each with a different set of 100 books,
لكل منها مجموعة مختلفة من 100 كتاب،
and so that village suddenly has 10,000 books.
وفجأة يكون لدى القرية 10 آلالاف كتاب.
You and I didn't have 10,000 books when we went to primary school.
ولم يكن لدينا 10 آلالاف كتاب عندما ذهبنا الى المدرسة الإبتدائية.
Sometimes school is under a tree,
بعض الأحيان المدرسة تحت الشجرة،
or in many cases, the teacher has only a fifth-grade education,
أو في كثير من الحالات، يدرّس المعلمون فقط خمس مستويات دراسية،
so you need a collaborative model of learning,
إذاً نحتاج لنموذج تعاوني للتعلم،
not just building more schools and training more teachers,
ليس فقط بناء مدارس أكثر وتدريب معلمين أكثر،
which you have to do anyway.
الشئ الذي ينبغي عليك فعله على أي حال.
So we're once again doing "Give One, Get One."
إذاً نحن نقوم مجدداً ب "أعطي واحد، خذ واحد."
Last year, we ran a "Give One, Get One" program,
العام الماضي، قمنا ببرنامج "أعطي واحد، خذ واحد،
and it generated over 100,000 laptops
وقد نتج عنه 100 ألف كمبيوتر محمول
that we were then able to give free.
بحيث أستطعنا تقديمها مجاناً.
And by being a zero-dollar laptop,
وكونه أصبح كمبيوتر محمول مجاني،
we can go to countries that can't afford it at all.
نستطيع الذهاب الى البلدان التي لا تستطيع الدفع بتاتاً.
And that's what we did. We went to Haiti,
وذلك ما فعلناه. ذهبنا الى هاييتي،
we went to Rwanda, Afghanistan,
وذهبنا الى رواندا، أفغانستان،
Ethiopia, Mongolia.
اثيوبيا، منغوليا.
Places that are not markets,
أماكن ليست أسواق،
seeding it with the principles of
نضع البذور لأساسيات
saturation, connectivity, low ages, etc.
التشبع، الربط، الأعمار المنخفضة، وهلمجرا.
And then we can actually roll out large numbers.
ومن ثم يمكننا فعلاً طرح أعداد أكبر.
So think of it this way:
إذاً فكروا فيها بهذه الطريقة
think of it as inoculating children
فكروا فيها بتحصين الأطفال
against ignorance.
من الجهل.
And think of the laptop as a vaccine.
وفكروا بالكمبيوترات المحمولة كاللقاح.
You don't vaccinate a few children.
أنتم لا تلقحون قلة من الأطفال
You vaccinate all the children in an area.
أنتم تلقحون كل الأطفال في المنطقة.